- Hey folks, and welcome to the video
on Lighting and Shadows.
Now, lighting and shadows might sound
like pretty boring topics.
And I don't blame you if you think that
but there's only one way to find out
and that's to watch this video.
I will say that lighting and
shadows is probably the source
of one of my earliest breakthroughs in UI
that just kind of made everything click.
And that is the simple idea
that light comes from the sky.
And if you bear this one idea
in mind that all the shadows that you put
into your user interface
are supposed to kind
of mimic real world lighting.
It's gonna make the whole
thing a lot easier, kind of
everything bubbles up from
that one little principle.
So we're gonna be talking
about how to craft a shadow,
what that implies about the light source
that's lighting up your UI,
and then we're gonna look
at a bunch of different
other kind of random tips
or tricks or tactics
for how to apply shadows
to your user interface design.
All right, enough intro.
All right, so let's talk about this light
comes from the sky idea,
that's a good place to start.
Light comes from the sky so often
whether you're outside and
it's the sun or you're inside
and it's a light on the
ceiling that, I mean
if you're sitting around a
campfire telling a scary story
we have this idea that
you shine a flashlight up,
light comes from the
bottom in order to make
your face look spooky, right?
So, it is so consistent that light comes
from the sky that even in our interfaces
which are totally flat you know,
pics colored pixels on a screen,
we still wanna imitate those
little lighting effects
and we still want to have those shadows.
And this is a perfect example of it.
This is, you know, from
back in the day, pre 2014
I think Apple's iPhone interface
had a lot more lighting
shadow, texture effects, stuff like that.
This has kind of fallen out of favor
but if we study how it used to be done
in highly skeuomorphic designs,
that's the designer a fancy term
for trying to imitate real world shadows
and textures and lighting effects.
If we look at how it's done
in a skeumorphic design,
we can pretty easily
apply those same lessons
to much flatter designs
where it's not quite as
vividly real world ask.
And you can see there's all sorts
of lighting and shadow
effects going on here.
There's kind of this
glossiness to this button,
there's a little highlight right here,
there's a shadow right here.
There's some texture,
which we're really not
gonna be covering texture in this lesson
but there's kind of this
little divot right here
that's got some shadowing effect,
on this switch there's a
bunch of stuff too, right?
It looks like this is sort of pressed in
and there's a little glossiness here
so there's, I mean, easily
half a dozen little effects.
Now, what I want to impress upon you
is that every single one of
these comes from the idea
of light coming from the sky.
So for instance, let's take
this little shadow right here.
This little shadow appears because
if there's some imaginary
light source shining
down on my interface, the ray
of sunlight passes
through here and hits here
but this area right here
does not get direct sunlight.
It just sort of maybe
catches some ambient line
so it's not exactly pitch black
but it's a little bit darker
because it doesn't catch
direct light from the sun.
Likewise, cause we're here,
let's say we have kind
of this glassy glossy texture right here,
some sort of material that
lines the inside of this switch.
Well, not only does this
part catch more light
because it's kind of directly
in line with the sun here.
You see this top part,
the sun's rays are kind
of only hitting it at a glancing blow.
It's gonna reflect some light,
but it's this bottom part
that's going to be
reflecting a lot more light
and that's kind of why we have
this glossiness right here.
If we go look at this little divot
you can see that it's
comprised of two lines.
There's sort of a darker line
on top of a lighter line.
And that's actually, that
was pretty surprising
to me when I first started
looking at this stuff.
This line right here, that's
kind of part of this divider
is actually lighter than the background.
Now, that is not necessary to
do in every single interface
but here it's just a really clear example
of what's going on.
We have light coming from the sky,
it sort of misses this top
part of the divot, right?
'Cause the sun can't really hit there
so that makes it darker.
And then this lighter part actually
receives the sun rays straight on
even compared to like this
surface area right here,
which is what makes this so light.
And so it's kind of cool
because when you zoom in enough
it doesn't really look like anything,
it looks like a dark line
on top of a white line.
But when you zoom out,
then your eye just sort
of takes it in as one
piece, which is kind of
this indented little
divot that runs the length
of these controls.
Of course, we're seeing similar stuff
on these buttons over here, the top
because it's a protruding button
with a popped out surface.
That top area is gonna catch more sunlight
and reflected right?
Here's the popped out button.
And this side gets more sunlight,
this side gets ever so slightly less.
They even have another
effect going on where
there's kind of a light bit
right inside the rim here.
And that sheen sort of implies
there's this perfect angle
at which the sun hits this
and goes straight to our
eyes very efficiently.
So this is skeuomorphic design.
This is when it's full of
lighting and shadows and textures.
Like I said, since about 2014,
this has really dropped off in popularity
and we really quickly went into an era
where everything became flat.
This is the idea of flat design,
there's no shadow effects,
there's no lighting effects.
They're still icons, they're still texts,
they're still even divider lines
but everything is a
little bit more symbolic.
It doesn't allude so strongly
to physical textures or physical effects.
Now this is a perfectly
valid way of designing today.
And to be fair, so is this,
although you might run into something
looking a little dated depending
on exactly how you do it
but honestly, most designs now
are somewhere in the middle.
They use the principles
from skeuomorphic design
but there's still plenty
of room to keep things
just very flat and clean looking.
So, as we explore these ideas,
we're gonna be looking primarily
at this little interface.
This is just a contact us
page, totally sample content
but it's gonna allow us
to kind of illustrate some
of the things we're talking about.
The first thing we should
do is actually break down
how shadows are created.
I'm gonna zoom in just so you
can see this pretty clearly
and figma, I'm gonna go do effects
and then the default effect
I can choose a couple of things,
including an inner shadow
we'll add some of those
but drop drop shadow is
the main one that I want.
And to actually set the
properties of the drop shadow,
I have to click this little
settings toggle icon right here.
Now you can see there's
actually four properties
I need a set.
X and Y a color and opacity for the color
a blur and something called a spread.
These are really not as
complicated as they sound.
The color should be fairly
apparent right off the get-go,
the default color of your
shadow is black and 99.9%
of the time that's what
you're gonna want to use.
Technically you could make
it red or some other color.
There's really not a
strong reason to do that.
The truth is any time the background
on which the shadow falls
has very little saturation,
let's say it's white or it's gray
or it's dark gray, or even black,
you can't see a shadow if it's pitch black
but if it's any sort of white
or gray and there's really
not too much color to it
it's kind of an off-white or an off-gray,
there's just no physical way
to have a shadow be colored
unless the button has like some
sort of lighting behind it.
And that's very much not
the style we're going
for 99.9% of the time.
So we'll keep our shadows black.
That's a fairly simple example.
We'll cover it more in the color unit
but you can run into colored shadows
if the background is not an a white
or an off-white or a gray
or kind of an off gray.
And so here's an example.
We'll actually look at this exact image,
but if I take like a little layer of black
and I try and match up with
this shadow color here,
let's see 10% opacities to
light, 20% still to light,
by 30 or 40 I'm starting
to get pretty close
to this color here
but you can see it's not
the exact same color.
This is a little bit richer of a red
and this is a little bit kind of flatter.
It's a little dollar in grayer
and we'll go into the
exact reason why that is.
But the lesson for us is that
unless your background is colored.
And even then if I was
putting a button on some sort
of Mingo salmon color or
whatever you call this,
I would still probably
just keep the button black
for simplicity sake.
If you're painting watercolors, go wild
but in the world of user interface design
99.9% of those shadows are gonna be black
and let's not overthink it.
Then there's the question of opacity.
This kind of represents the
strength of the light source.
You can see that if I
have an opacity of 0%,
there's no shadow at all.
And if I have no capacity of
say 50%, it's pretty strong.
Of course, I can also do
an opacity of a hundred
which means I'm gonna be getting
to a pure black right
there where the shadow
is at its strongest, I
almost never want that.
Again just to kind of give
you the 80-20 rule here.
I would say 80% of the
time, you're just gonna
want a shadow that starts
at about around 20%.
Maybe sometimes you'll bump it
up to 25%, maybe down to 15.
But I would say that 20
to 25 opacity is really
the sweet spot for shadows
on light backgrounds.
Occasionally you'll want
a very light shadow,
it's not uncommon to have
something that's at 5% or 10%
especially if the shadow
is a little bit larger.
So it's what it loses in
the strength of the shadow
it makes up for in the size.
You also might have a
particularly dark shadow
that's 35% or even 40%.
I find that most of the time
if you're gonna be using
a value like 35 or 40,
it's because you actually
have a dark background.
So if we just go look at some
of these interface elements
that I have designed
in the past, that logo didn't
come through, that's weird.
You can see, let's see,
this is an opacity of 30%
just a very thin little
shadow on a light background
but something like this could
be quite a bit darker, 50%.
And that is just because
since the background is darker
a shadow needs to be
correspondingly darker
in order to come through
sort of the same amount.
Even though I've spent a
lot of this unit harping
on you like being
consistent in everything,
you honestly don't really
need to be consistent
about exactly how strong shadows are.
I feel like the main goal here is to
make the shadows appear
generally sort of consistent
but as we'll see later
on, in some examples,
consistency is honestly not
as important for lighting
and shadows as it is for
other aspects of your design.
Now, the X and Y properties
and the next ones to cover.
And these are just dead simple.
The X affects the sort
of the horizontal position of the shadow.
Zero means it's perfectly
centered while I suppose
at some level you could be kind of cutesy
and say that like you have
a sunset lighting effect
and the sun is really off to the side.
If the sun is more or less above you
you're just always gonna
be using zero here.
And as you'll see in this video,
I don't think we ever change this value
unless perhaps we're doing some sort
of special lighting effect that isn't just
like an element that's slightly raised
from the screen casting a shadow.
The Y value on the other hand, I mean this
so this affects the vertical
position of this shadow.
We're often just gonna have
a small positive value.
And that just means the shadow falls
below the object that's
raised up because light comes
from the sky and cast the
shadow below the element.
I don't think I've ever designed something
that had lighting coming from below
and therefore needed a negative Y value.
Although sometimes when you do
internal shadows to elements
which we'll see in just a bit,
you will play around with that
Y value a little bit more.
No that for default shadows,
a good Y value is typically
one pixel two pixels.
Usually I don't go much more
than four pixels and we'll talk
about why in just a minute,
oh, no pun intended.
All right, moving on to blur.
The blur property has to do
with how focused the light sources
and also the distance between
the object and the shadow
which because of the refraction of light
those are actually the same things
but you don't really need to worry
about the physics too much.
The important idea is
that, well, blur is kind of
what it sounds like if
I have no blur at all,
I have a hard edge to the shadow.
It just looks like someone
threw another rectangle
below my button.
If I have a massive blur,
let's say 40 pixels,
then I get this very soft shadow effect
which actually really does
have a time and a place.
Blur is a very powerful property though
and it definitely has an
ability to be much higher
than whatever you're
using for this Y value.
So sometimes I think I
might see a blur that's less
than the Y, but for the most part
it's actually honestly
a little bit bigger.
With such a large Y value
in such a large blur
I'd probably reduce the opacity
of this just to kind of make
up for it and end up with a
little bit more subtle shadow.
Now, the final property
that we have to talk
about is the spread.
And this one's a bit of a doozy
because it represents
something totally unrealistic
and real life, which is
it allows you to
artificially change the size
of the object, casting the shadow.
So with a spread value of 20,
the shadow is actually going
out 20 pixels beyond where
it otherwise would have.
It's sort of artificially saying
let's pretend this button
is 20 pixels bigger,
I believe on every single side
and then display the
shadow for that thing.
Likewise, you can also
have a negative spread
which like in this case
just made it disappear
but if the spread is just
negative a little bit,
it kind of sucks the shadow in.
This has an effect of making the element
look a little bit closer to the viewer
to quote unquote the camera.
It's as if this element is
popped out of the screen so much
it's obscuring us from
seeing its own shadow.
So that's kind of what
a negative spread does.
As we'll talk about in a sec,
if you have a negative spread,
sometimes you actually want
to increase the strength
of the shadow to make up
for that and actually make
it a little more visible.
But playing with spreads
is useful for a number
of interesting lighting
effects and shadow effects
but also can be used
just to create kind of
these very soft shadows with
elements that need to appear
like they're just
hovering over the screen.
All right.
So if we're putting this all together,
let's try and just kind
of look at quote unquote
a totally normal shadow.
Like if you're just creating
a shadow on some element
for the first time, what
values should you put in here?
Well, I think different
people have slightly
different tastes, but
usually what I default
to and you'll see me do this
throughout the course is having a shadow
of say about a Y value of one
which means it's gonna be
below the button itself.
And it's gonna have a blur
that's a little bit larger
than that Y value.
So this could be one and two,
this could be two and three right here.
It might even be two and
four, whatever it is,
this is getting pretty dark.
At this point, I get in here
and adjust this opacity down probably
to something like 20% again,
a good place to default.
And then by default, for most shadows
I'm not really gonna have much spread
and by not much, I mean zero,
let's be totally clear here.
So let's say we do wanna
use that type of shadow,
I'll go and actually
replace our current button
with our new shadowed button here.
And then even though I said
that shadowing is not as
important consistency wise,
we still wanna kind of default
to it and see how that works.
So we'll talk about a couple
of cases where maybe it doesn't
work as well for instance.
Again, looking at our
properties here, Y value
of two to a blur of four
and an opacity of 20%.
If we hop on up to this header up here,
we have this very light gray
header at the top of the page.
Headers are something
that if they're not flat,
that is if they have any shadow at all
the shadow is gonna be below them.
Headers are never inset into the page.
Instead I call them outset.
I realized that is inventing a new usage
of the English word outset.
It's a new definition,
that's not what it means.
But just bear with me, Inset
and outset are opposites
for the purposes of this course.
And headers are always outset,
these sort of top navigation
elements like that.
So in that case
I know I'm gonna want
to put a shadow below.
We'll go and we'll just do,
I think we said it was two and four
and 25% or something
like that, or actually
it was 20% wasn't it?
Just gave us a little lecture
on outsets and already
forgot my shadow value.
Yeah, two and four 20%, there we go.
All right.
So this is interesting
because maybe I can
actually reduce this just
to make it a little more apparent here.
You could run into this case where
if you have a particularly light object
that's casting the shadow,
sometimes the shadow
itself kind of blends in
with the object or it's
sort of tough to see
where the shadow begins and
where the object begins,
or it's tough to see where the shadow ends
and where the object begins.
This makes it a little bit
more apparent, but now looking
at this, it's like, am I
looking at a border here?
And this is the element
or is this just like
where the shadow ends?
And if you zoom out,
you'll notice it actually
appears a little bit fuzzier to one's eye.
This also happens if I'm using
say like a very bright color.
Sometimes if I have yellow
and the yellow's casting
a shadow, that shadow
does the same thing where my
eye has trouble distinguishing
where the light object casting
the shadow ends and where
that light shadow begins.
So that's something to be careful of
and certainly a reason to be inconsistent
with how you apply your shadows.
Certainly I could fix it
by removing the shadow.
That's perfectly valid
because shadows are almost
always optional in UI design now,
but another good way
to do this is I really
shouldn't actually have
a light gray header
in the first place, because
if light comes from the sky
the things that are more
popped out of the screen
are gonna be just slightly
more available to catch
the sun's rays and
reflect it into our eyes.
And anything that's indented
down into the screen,
which the main screen is indented relative
to the header should
actually be slightly darker.
That's a good general rule to follow.
Not saying you always
need to, but it's going to
sort of naturally assist with
how the eye perceives things.
So if anything,
I'm actually gonna try
and make this white.
Now, I don't actually want to
make the rest of the screen
a very light gray, but I certainly could.
And then I have some shadow here
which nominal adjust isn't
necessarily gonna be consistent
with exactly how I do the
shadow on this button.
No, not necessarily, but that's
kind of my thought process
and putting a shadow
on something like this.
If we're gonna go do a text box here,
we get into some new territory
because text boxes usually
if they are not flat,
if they have a shadow at
all, they're usually indented
into the screen and we're
gonna do it that way
so we can talk about inner shadows.
Now I need to switch from drop
shadow to inner shadow here.
And I find that I have actually
the exact same properties.
I can go and I can kinda NAB
these down to two for 20%
and you can see that
that's actually quite a bit
of dark shadow inside
the element right there.
And we've talked about
this idea in spacing and
in the simplicity lesson, that
shadows are really there to
kind of convey some information
about how all the objects
are related, but they're
more like metadata,
they're more like a meta
element that says something
about a relationship
rather than actual content.
And anything like that can
actually be pretty light.
It just needs to be lightness
so that you can perceive
it's there even if unconsciously.
I guess that's not even
technically true of shadows
if they're not required,
but if we're gonna bother
to put one, we're gonna make it
so that it's just ever so perceivable
but we don't really need
to make it all that dark.
This Seems like it's working pretty well
but one thing that I would
be concerned about is
if you make the blur too
large and an inner shadow
at some point, you're
gonna have shadow coming up
from the bottom too.
And that just does not make much sense.
So if you start to see on an
inner shadow shadow coming up
from the bottom, then you
know you've probably blurred
too much and you need to
kind of back things up
a little bit.
Once we have with shadow
that we like here,
I can use option command
C to copy it and option
command V to paste it right here
and that just copies and
paste the style and figma.
Now I'm not actually gonna
copy and paste the style
from this button, but
this dropdown right here
drop downs are another control
that most traditionally
if they're not flat, they're
raised up out of the screen.
So I'm just gonna go and
quickly add in a little a shadow
right here.
There we go.
And again, it can be quite subtle.
It just needs to kind of barely register
on the user's consciousness
at minimum that it's there.
And that shadow kind of
says, hey, I'm clickable,
come click me.
Likewise, the inner
shadow here in here says,
I'm typable, click in and start typing.
Now, ultimately the shadow
values that we've picked
for this button are kind of
on the low end of things.
Two and four are the Y value in the blur,
I just wanna show you
it is possible that you
will have scenarios where
you will get much greater values here.
And one of the biggest cases for doing so
is because you're trying
to represent elevation.
Now, let's talk briefly
kind of the naive idea
of how you might make
something appear elevated
is to increase the Y value.
But realistically, it's not
like this button looks
elevated when I do this.
You know, even if I were
to kind of move it up,
like that doesn't feel quite
right and it's not quite right
because like I said slightly earlier,
one of the things that
happens is when the object
that cast the shadow gets
farther away from the shadow,
this edge gets more diffuse,
we need to increase the blur value
in addition to increasing the Y value.
So typically, the way I think about this
is I will move these up, I
will kind of multiply them.
It might work just fine if you
add like two to each of them
but I'll do something
where I just multiply each
by two or even by one and a half.
So two and four is going
to become four and eight
and then we can do this again.
And now, if you look at these
three one after the other,
it does really start to look
like this one is kind of
hovering higher than this one.
And this effect can be used to say
if you want different elements
to slide over one another
you can give certain things, quote unquote
a higher elevation and those
things will appear on top
when you're scrolling, you
can have certain controls
that are the most popped out
from the screen, et cetera.
But one of them primary use cases
for something like this is
say doing a hover state.
And the idea is perhaps
when I hover on this button,
I actually want the shadow
to get a little bit bigger,
which means the effect we're
trying to simulate it's
as if, when I hover on this
button, the button rises
up a little bit from the screen.
And actually material design
has something very similar
where not only do they have
the button rise up on hover
but when then when I click
my mouse down right here
it comes up even a little bit more.
So there's sort of this
progression, the button actually
kind of rises up out of
the screen to meet you
as you go to click it.
That's not the only way to
do it Clicked state, right?
Certainly another option is if this button
if the analogy that I want to
follow should be pressed in,
I can pick like a slightly
darker shade of the button
and then instead of having
a shadow on the outside
give it an inner shadow
and this makes this button
look pressed in.
So if I click here, it's
as if my little mouse
cursor is pressing this into
the screen and it suddenly
becomes indented, which not
only gives it a slightly
darker background color,
because again, indentation
will most naturally always
mean a darker background color
but then there's also that
inner shadow to really
drive the metaphor home.
All right, so hopefully
that makes some sense.
The big thing to remember is elevation
is simulated with movement
in both the Y and the blur.
And just to drive the point
home, I wanna show you
that this actually does
happen in the real world.
If you look at this example,
this makes it crystal clear
but the shadow from this
woman's chin on her neck is,
has a very crisp delineation
between what's shadowed and what's light,
it has a very clear boundary.
The shadow from the trees
which are farther away, and
yet like half an inch away
on the surface of her neck,
these are much fuzzier.
And that is simply because
the tree is farther away.
The light has actually, it's
gone just around the tree
and it started to spread
out kind of lightly
and it gives us this effect.
Likewise, you can see this.
I mean, this is fun if you
ever got at sunset, but look
at the crispness of the shadow
of his feet and his legs,
where there's a very small distance
between the object casting the shadow
and the shadow itself and his
head, which is much fuzzier
or what's even fuzzier is
the shadow that's being cast
from further away, this building here
and that's the fuzziest
shadow of all of them.
So this sort of just,
I think makes very clear
this real-world way
in which shadows work
that we are trying to
imitate when we're creating
elevation in our UI.
Now in my book, hover States are one
of those things that to really
get the feel of the design
of a hover state, you actually
have to try it out like
in your browser and see,
does this feel like too much?
Does it feel like not enough?
And whenever I'm designing a hover state
I kind of say mentally,
I reserve the right to
change my mind here.
But we do have in Figma, there's kind of,
at least at this point
it's a little bit of a hack
to show a hover state but I
could take my hovered button
and if I unclick the clip content property
that allow the shadow to shine out
around this little frame right
here, and then I got to go
to the prototype tab and
add a little interaction.
I don't want to click interaction,
I want a well hovering interaction
and this is going to be opened
as an overlay quote unquote,
we'll go grab button hover.
And I want to say that it
should be positioned manually
which means that this
little frame right here
by default will appear right over
the thing that's being hovered on.
Now, this should be enough
where I can go press play
and let's see how this
looks when I hover on it.
Hey, not too bad.
That actually feels
pretty good in my opinion.
Now because this other button
is added as an overlay,
there's technically, I'm
looking at two shadows here.
This is a little darker
than I would be seeing in
browser, but what can you do?
It's better than nothing and sometimes
it's worth exploring just to kind of test
your intuitions about hover States.
So we've kind of talked
about the standard shadow.
We've talked about how
to simulate elevation.
Let's talk a little bit more
about those softer shadows.
The soft shadows that you
see with negative spread,
those often work best on larger elements.
So if I go and I create something here,
let's give it a blur that's
actually four times larger
than the Y value here.
So that's gonna be fairly
large as far as blurs go
and I'm just gonna make it a
little darker so we can see it.
What I've done is
actually created a fairly
large amount of shadow.
You could like go figure
out what is the area
that is very noticeably gray
because it's the entire length
on both the top and bottom
and the entire height on
both the left and the right
that has all become much grayer.
Now, the thing that's kind of beautiful
about having a negative spread
is it sucks the shadow in,
it pretends the object casting,
it is a little bit smaller
But what that means is the
shadow starts to disappear
around the corners.
So if you see here, I still
have this gray that runs most
of the length of the image itself
but right around the
corners, it kind of fades out
and I can actually play
this effect even more.
Let me increase the blur.
Let's go to something like huge
like even 40 pixels or
something like that.
And then as I decrease the spread more,
that just means more
and more of the effect
of the shadow is it's going
to be visible kind of here,
like a little disc peeking out,
a little half disc peeking out right there
not even half, sorry, it's
just a fraction of a disc.
You have this kind of shadow
peeking out ever so slightly
but even around the corners,
it's all but disappeared.
So when you have very large
objects that need to be raised
up from the screen, playing
with this negative spread
value can be a way to do it.
Do you remember that for a
shadow of equal visibility,
if you have a negative spread,
you do want to be bumping
up the opacity, just so
it's actually visible.
Otherwise it's gonna be, I mean
just completely invisible.
(indistinct) to be perfectly fair,
this is a contrived example
because I think this little
like beacon might be clickable.
For instance, maybe it would
bring up a little thing calling
out the address or the
phone number or something.
This map by itself would
probably not be clickable
and therefore, I wouldn't
really wanna give it
a good shadow treatment like this.
A shadow treatment often
implies clickability
and I guarantee if you watch people,
they might hover over this map and try
and figure out what
they can click on here.
Now, this is sort of a big
example, but I will just say
in the same way that I kind
of have a go-to default shadow
of about one to two here two
to four here in 20% here,
my default shadow if I'm
going to do a negative spread
is to put in some value for
Y actually use the equal
and opposite value for the
spread and then use something
like four times that value for the blur.
This is often how I think
about kind of a nice,
good soft shadow.
Now I'm not really sure
exactly what I would want to
do to optimize this 'cause
it doesn't necessarily
make a ton of sense on the
map here, but you can kind
of see, even if I have,
let's say 25% okay,
you get a sense that there's
a shadow underneath there.
It's pretty subtle and
it's ever so much lighter
at the little corners here.
Now let's talk about the
spread value a little bit more
because in this example,
we use the spread value
in conjunction with a large positive blur.
But one of my favorite little
effects is to add a shadow
where the shadow is not
actually representing the shadow
from a light source it's
representing light itself.
So, I'm gonna go to the shadow
and the first thing I'm
gonna change very noticeably
is I'm gonna grab this
color, the same color
as the little beacon here and that's gonna
be my light color.
Then I'm gonna center the
shadow on the beacon itself.
Right now you can see it
already looks like it's glowing,
so technically I could call it right there
but I found it can be very
cool to reduce the blur to zero
which now there's no shadow.
But if I start to give it
a positive spread, well,
nothing happens until you can see
that this is actually supposed
to be only 50% opacity.
So I can increase the
spread as much as I want.
I could even animate it.
This could be a beacon that
sort of shoots out some light
and disappears, shoots out
some light and disappears.
There's all kinds of fun effects there
that you can work with.
By using a positive spread
with no blur is just a nice
little way to create some sort
of like beacon indicator or whatever.
And your developer, if they don't know
about it already will
always appreciate this
because if they can add this as a shadow
rather than as a separate element,
it's just slightly less work for them.
Another place where this is
super handy is a focus state.
So let's say I click
into this email address,
little input right here.
Well, one thing I'm gonna wanna do is
especially if someone is, I said click
but especially if someone
is using say tab to get
around and they're just
tabbing through the interface,
then we need to show in some
way when this field is focused
because the user didn't
necessarily click there,
they press tab and then
their eye needs to track
where did focus move to?
Well, probably my all-time
favorite way to do that is with
I mean, you can do it with
a shadow or you could do it
with an outline in this case, let's do it
with a quote unquote drop shadow.
That's really not a shadow at all,
it's almost like a glow.
So we're gonna center it
again, X and Y of zero
then we're gonna go pick some fun color.
We could just use our theme purple,
there's no reason not to do that.
And we're gonna do that same playbook,
reduce the blur, increase the spread.
Right now this is pretty hefty
but let's just bring down
the opacity a little bit,
something like 30% bring down that spread.
All I need to do is make this
spread high enough where when
someone presses tab and their
cursor and goes into this box
and they can start typing,
their eye is just ever
so drawn right there.
And I think this would work fairly well.
Are you ready for a third
trick related to spread?
This one is pretty good too.
So, let's go look at this other example.
Maybe I have some sort of book reading app
and I've got all these
images of books here.
One thing you can do with a
negative spread is actually
make a shadow that
appears only on the bottom
and doesn't appear on the sides at all.
How do you do that you ask?
Let me tell you.
First, you're gonna make sure
you have a positive Y value
and you're also gonna
want a positive blur,
but then the spread needs
to be negative enough
so that it counteracts
the effect of the blur.
The shadow is normally
blurring out from the sides
and it's equal on both sides.
And if it's a blur for
it'll probably go out,
let's say roughly four
pixels although I don't know
if it's always exact.
If I have a spread of negative four,
it's sucks that shadow in.
So let's actually make it
just a little bit darker
so we can see what
we're working with here.
So now you can see the shadow,
I'm gonna go into pixel mode too.
There we go.
And then when I do my negative
spread, the shadow is all
about gone now with the spread
of negative three, except for
on the bottom, because I
had this positive Y value,
the shadow is always just been
shifted down a little bit.
So now it's invisible on the top,
it's invisible on the sides
but the spread counteracts
the blur enough that it's only visible
on the bottom because of the positive Y.
Let's go see how this looks.
Zoom out, it's not quite
as strong as I was hoping.
I'm gonna bring down the opacity, kind of
fix this bad boy up a little
bit, increase the Y there.
And I wanna make it look
a little more blurred
and there we go.
Maybe that blur is now making
it visible on the sides
but to me honestly,
that looks good enough.
Now there's technically another way
to do bottom only shadows
and that is instead of
doing it with a shadow
it is to use a whole
separate layer to do that.
And typically the way I do
it is with a blurred layer.
So I'm gonna press O to create new oval
and then I'm just gonna draw
my oval right under a book.
I'm actually gonna make it black
because that's the default
color of shadows all the time.
And let's go ahead
and use a different
effect, not a drop shadow.
We're gonna use a layer blur.
Here it is.
And the default layer blur Figma throws on
is for definitely not enough,
I want something higher.
20 yeah, that should be good enough.
Now let's actually get this
layer blur below the book,
I can do that.
And then I can mess with the opacity too.
So maybe say 50% or something
like that is closer to what I want.
I'll go ahead and duplicate
it just a couple of times
because it's always better to
evaluate this sort of stuff
when you can see it all.
Let's try a lighter opacity, 30%.
Yeah, something like that
could work really nicely.
Now this is cool too
because this gives me the
option of having something
that's floating high enough off
the screen where the shadow,
I can see the entire shadow, right?
Like here's the dark
point and then it's clear
that it's floating this entire
distance off the screen.
It's not like the shadow is
forced to be sort of attached
to the element, which is the case
if I'm using an actual drop shadow.
So that's just another fun effect
or kind of way to do things.
I will say there is one
other fairly common way
of representing shadows
that you should know about.
So far, we've talked about using
like Figma is actual shadow effect,
and then we talked about blurring
a black oval here and then
making it less opaque.
But sometimes you can actually
just represent a shadow
with a black shape that's not blurred
and then just given some light opacity.
And if you're doing illustration,
like this is how your shadows
will look in illustration.
You'll often just use
a different color layer
and make it the shape of the shadow.
So I don't have any illustrations
on this particular page
but one thing I could do,
and this is kind of fun
if a little gimmicky is make
this book, actually look
like a hard cover by sort of
faking where a shadow would go.
That sort of represents
that fold between the spine
of the book and the cover of the book.
And so if I'm gonna do that,
I'm actually going to have
a little gradient here.
I'll switch over to a linear gradient
and then I'm gonna drag one
part there, one part there
and I'm actually, of course
I'm just gonna make it black.
Sorry, that is the color of shadows
and I want this to work
pretty across the board,
obviously that's way too dark.
So maybe I bring it down to something
like 20% opacity and there we
go, it looks a little bit more
like a hard cover, and
I could take this sort
of gimmick and apply it to all the books.
Probably won't be very visible
on the dark cover there.
That might be a little more
visible there but perfect.
Now I've got three different
ways of making shadows.
I can use a, just a layer proper,
I can use a blurred layer
representing the shadow
or I can use the shadow
property in my app.
But in all of these cases,
everything we've done so far
has only one shadow per layer.
And sometimes you actually want
multiple shadows per layer.
Why would you want that?
Because there's multiple light sources.
So one place where I most
commonly a map to do this
isn't something like a
floating action button
which needs to float above
all the other content
on the page and it's
just a good way to demo
what multiple light sources can look like.
Now, certainly the first
thing that we're gonna do
is we're gonna go and create
a fairly high elevation shadow
just the standard way.
So maybe instead of
saying one and two here,
I say four and eight.
That's a good place to start
if it's a pretty high up shadow 25%
maybe I'll make it just
a little bit higher just
to make it a little more apparent.
There we go.
So I have this floating action
button that does indeed look
like it's floating,
I could probably even make
this look a little bit more.
Let's try something like six and 12.
Yeah, there we go.
Now in cinema, this is known as the shadow
from the key light.
The key light is like the
main light that is providing
that light from above and
light on the scene here.
That is not the only light source.
And when I say it's not
the only light source,
actually maybe I'm playing fast and loose
with the language here
because the other light source
that I'm referencing is ambient light.
That's light that bounces around, bounces
off all the other stuff in
the room and hits, you know
here or your object or whatever
and kind of casts a very
very light shadow.
To create an ambient shadow,
all I'm gonna do is it
has no directionality
since it's light bouncing
off of everything
or it has very little, you know
there might be some you'd have to talk
to somebody knows this better.
So in order to represent
it for our purposes
I'm gonna make it
centered X and Y of zero.
And then I'm gonna give it
a pretty hefty blur too.
But I'm just gonna make
sure that it's very light,
it's gonna be almost imperceptible.
But one of the things that it will do is
it's gonna be easiest
to perceive at the top,
because one issue that you
can have with your shadows is
if they're very strongly
biased to below the button
the shadow can be so light at
the top that it's hard to see.
It's not really a problem
with a deep purple button like this
but if my button was actually much lighter
then I'd wanna make sure
there's enough shadow
at the top so that it
does not appear to blend
in with the background here.
And that's one thing an
ambient shadow can be good
at doing.
So you can't see it as much up there
but then keep your eye kind
of just to top the control
and it's gonna get a little
darker, especially there.
Okay, so that's plenty
of stuff with shadows.
I wanna talk about a few
other lighting effects
that are more kind of the
gleams and glints that come
off of things rather than
the shadows below them.
Probably the most common
you'll see is you'll
have a little bit of a
bevel, which just implies
that the edge of this is not
like a perfect 90 degree angle,
sort of the edge if you were
to picture this thing in 3D
but instead there is a
bevel all the way around.
And the most common way of doing that is
with a stroke where the
stroke has a gradient.
So I'll do a linear gradient
of course and the top part
of this gradient is actually
gonna start at white, okay?
And we'll, you'll see,
I'll change the color here.
It's not gonna be pure white,
but the idea is this is
what's catching the light and
reflecting it into our eyes.
This bevel at the bottom
side is angled away
from the light source
and so it's going to
be a little bit darker.
We can just do pure black, who cares?
We'll adjust this in just a second
and you'll see how it looks much better.
Certainly the easiest
and kind of naive way
to adjust it is just
to change the opacity.
But I don't actually prefer that.
I feel like it works just slightly better
if we change the blend mode.
So as a strangely, the case
with most of this course
overlay in soft light
are like the blend modes
are gonna be going to the most.
Overlay here, I feel like it
changes it into two different
of a color, so let's
go look at soft light.
Oh yeah, bingo, this is it.
Now, what I wanna do is take whichever one
appears maybe a little bit too strong
and just kind of bump
that down a little bit.
So it feels like it matches the top here.
And then what I'm gonna
do is I'm just gonna
make it extra visible,
I'll make it two pixels
but that's not required.
When I zoom out, you
can now see the bevel.
It appears maybe just a bit too strong,
so I'll take the entire
thing down just a little bit,
so that here we go, maybe 60%.
Now, if I remember correctly,
it's not actually possible
in CSS to specify a blend mode
for a border on an object that
doesn't have a blend mode.
So if I was making this on the web,
I'd probably in order to
give this to a developer
have to sample this color
directly and this one directly
and say, just make a border
that has a linear gradient
from this color to this color.
But for the sake of design, we know
at least how we can get
there and get that effect.
Now we started down the
road to skeuomorphism
and who wants to turn
around now, instead when
I see the kind of this bevel,
it makes me also think what
if I could just make this button
ever so slightly indented?
Well, very possible effect.
Whenever you want to indent something,
think about how the sun is hitting it.
The light source from the sky comes
and hits the bottom more directly
which means it reflects
more light into your eye.
The top gets less light, the
light is kind of hitting it
at a glancing blow, so it's
gonna be a little bit darker.
So I'm gonna do that same
sort of linear gradient,
this time with another fill layer.
I'll put it on linear gradients starts
at black and goes to
100% right at the bottom.
Again am gonna have to go and
try out a different blend mode
to get even close to the effect I want.
But in all likelihood,
I'm gonna take this down.
Let's say got to zoom out a little bit
so I can see the grids.
There we go.
Something like 20% should
probably be enough.
Perfect, it's super
super subtle, but it just
gives you an idea of what
you can do when you wanna try
out other lighting effects.
By the way, I would say for most buttons,
it's far more common to see
the button that's popped out
rather than slightly indented in.
And so this linear gradient
fill is actually gonna be
from white on top to black on the bottom.
We'll see a few examples of that later.
Now, if we really have a problem
and just can't stop ourselves
from adding lighting effects,
kind of the next thing that
demands to be done here.
And this is not an effect,
I think I've used
professionally since like 2013
or so, is to actually have
this icon appear slightly
debossed.
Debossed is the opposite of embossing,
embossing is when something's popped out,
debossing is when say text or in this case
an icon is actually pushed
in just a little bit.
Now, if we consider our light
source coming from the top
then light is very directly
going to hit anything
that's angled up, but it's
going to have a glancing blow
for the things at the top
where it's kind of angled in.
So one way to do this
is with an inner shadow.
Go and add our effects here and our shadow
and let's do a Y of zero or
a blur of zero, excuse me
'cause we don't have any
space to work with here.
This is kind of all we got
just has to look like that.
But even something like
that, that's a little strong
but let's zoom out and see how it looks.
There we go.
It may be a bit tough to see
on the video that you're
watching in this course
but it's something that
you can play around with
and it's a perfectly valid
effect for this sort of thing.
Now, one thing I want to tell you
that's just overall important
and kind of a meta lesson
beyond any individual thing I'm saying
in this lesson is to
always go and check kind of
how other good designers
are doing lighting
and shadowing effects.
Like for instance,
if I knew I had to make some progress bar
to represent a book that I've
read some certain percentage
of, I could go and do a bunch of research
to generally figure out
like do I make this pushed
into the screen or do
I make it popped out?
Is it indented?
Is it out dented?
What is it?
And if I did that
I would find almost universally
that these are indented.
The progress bar itself is indented,
so let's go and add that.
And that the fill for the
progress bar is out dented.
And I'm gonna give it a very light opacity
because this thing actually
could be a light source itself,
so I really don't want it to get too dark.
Something that emits light
is not gonna have a very
very shaded bottom to it.
And fair enough,
that's how to handle it
if it's a progress liner.
But overall, I think it's
important to keep this
in mind about every single control here.
For instance, we've seen that buttons
I mean always have shadows below them,
buttons are always out dented.
Anything that kind of resembles
a card, it's the same story.
In fact, it's really at this point
it's just a very common beginner
mistake for me to see where
if you stick with the
frames, default background
color of white and then you
have something that looks
like a card on your UI,
you might be tempted to make
it a light gray instead.
But if you make it a light
gray, like ask yourself,
does this look like
something that's popped out
of the screen or pushed into the screen?
At least to my eyes.
And I think this is kind of
accepted designer wisdom,
anything that's darker appears pushed in.
Well, I'm really shooting
myself in the foot
then if I'm trying to
make this look like a card
with the main content, so
this needs to be white.
And if I'm gonna have a
color difference at all
then I'm gonna make the whole
background this light gray.
Of course, as we talked about in spacing
you have other ways of doing that.
You could use a divider line
or you could just use a shadow, et cetera.
But the important thing
to remember is these cards
are always popped out
any sort of card content
along with any sort of button
headers of the same way,
these are always out dented.
I will say that most of the time
if they're not flat
drop-downs are out dented
but text inputs have a
little bit more leeway.
It's possible to see some text inputs
especially big search
inputs that are out dented
and have a shadow below
them rather than indented.
Of course, we'll look
at some examples now,
probably the most common thing now
is to actually have
totally flat text boxes,
but just know you have
a little bit more leeway
with text boxes.
And speaking of leeway,
radios and checkboxes are
also kind of the same thing.
You don't universally
see that a radio button
or a checkbox is out dented or indented.
So let's look at a couple
of examples just to wrap things up.
As I mentioned earlier in the lesson,
consistency is just weirdly less important
with shadows than it
is with other aspects.
Say like the font style
here totally consistent,
the colors are consistent,
the layout is consistent
but here I have a little search
bar that's completely flat.
Although look at this.
When I have a focus state here it's made
from sort of that exterior shadow
with no blur and a positive
spread, that's awesome.
Anyhow, it's a totally
flat text box right here
but then right here this, I
mean, it's the same search.
It even says the same thing in each one.
And if I were to type in
more here in at present
or then I would see it update right here
and yet this one is not flat.
This one has a nice, big,
soft shadow below it.
So you have a little bit more room
for these kinds of inconsistencies.
You can make some things flat
and some things much more shadowed.
In general, I would try and be consistent
within like one type though, like yes,
I realize these are both search bars
but this is sort of the big,
the big display search bar
and this is the tiny one up in the menu.
If I look here, here's a drop down
that's actually very
consistent with this button
which is not a dropdown.
They're styled exactly
the same, both flat.
And then I can tap in here and sure enough
see that despite all
this stuff being flat,
at least these search bars are consistent
with this top search bar right here.
So dribble has very few shadows.
The invoicing app harvest
is something that comes
to mind as a little more
skeuomorphic of an app.
You can see, they have a
lighting effect on their header.
Interestingly enough, they
don't have a shadow below it
but they do have sort of this gradient
from a brighter orange
because this is catching
the sun's rays better because
it's angled towards it
and then this bottom is
just a little bit darker.
So it's kind of as if
this header is out dented
from the screen just a little bit.
It's even more clearly visible
in this dropdown right here,
right?
This dropdown is very light at the top.
I mean, it's very light
at the bottom as well
but it is slightly darker at the bottom,
same thing with this button here.
Interesting that when
I hover on it, it looks
like it keeps the effect, but
it just makes both the top
and the bottom a little bit darker.
With this sort of hover effect,
one thing I like in this
two is, it's as if you know,
I was moving my hand over the button
and that sort of shadows
the element itself
'cause it blocks the sun
from hitting it as
directly or as strongly.
But I definitely prefer hover
states that are a bit darker
Now, despite all the shadowing
on these elements above,
it looks like their text
box is totally flat.
There's no shadow whatsoever.
And then I get down here and
it appears that there's almost
these buttons that are kind of like tabs.
It's a bit tough to say, but
these are flatter themselves
than the other buttons that we've seen.
So it's sort of like a secondary style
that's not perfectly consistent
being totally flat,
there's no shadows there.
Same thing with check boxes,
And I just wanna say that
you should never ever
ever have any shadows on
a control that's disabled.
If I can't use this control, it's disabled
because I've said that this is
not a billable type of task.
If I can't click in here, there
should not be any shadows.
Shadows, they don't
always imply clickability
but a lot of the time they do.
And it's just a very
industry standard thing
to have no shadows on a disabled control.
A good example of this is Duolingo
which actually has totally flat shadows.
Like they might be doing
the shadow with an internal
like an internal shadow
that's just a slightly
darker shade of green here,
but despite kind of the cartoony shadow
on the save button here,
this is a totally flat text input box.
And then if we look at
this motivational message
this little slider here,
you'll notice the sort
of the track of the
slider is this flat blue.
But then if anything, it's sort of implied
that this button that slides
back and forth is popped
out of the screen because it
has the dark area below it,
right?
So again, if I do slide this such that I
haven't made any changes
that green shadow disappears
and it's a totally flat gray.
So all in all, I appreciate the design
of all three of these
sites and yet they're going
for a bunch of different effects, right?
Here's a very cartoony, bubbly feel
very friendly brand that
has sort these almost
cartoonish shadows applied to it.
And then we have something
that's a little bit
more skeuomorphic, it's certainly not
like the old iOS looked
but it's a little bit
more along those lines.
And then we have something
that's almost entirely flat
but just has this very
tastefully applied soft
shadow right here.
But like I've said almost
the most important metal
lesson you can have coming out of this,
is just to go and look at examples
whenever you need to design a control.
If you're wondering how you
should apply shadow somewhere,
don't just guess at it,
like go see what there is.
Because once you start
consciously noticing this stuff
you're gonna pick up on
little effects and trends
and ways of doing things
that you just didn't notice.
They were just all totally unconscious
until you start analyzing these things.
So light comes from the sky, right?
Remember that and you'll be (indistinct),
all the rest is more or less just details.
In all seriousness,
probably the toughest thing
with lighting and
shadows is in that stage,
when you realize you're
gonna need to create
all the different form elements
and kind of have them
look somewhat consistent
even if the individual
shadows vary or some
of the controls are flat
and others are shadowed,
you kind of figure out how
exactly do we get everything
to work so that it
looks consistent enough,
even if it's not truly as if
there's just one light source
that shines on everything identically.
So, because that's the tough part
that's gonna be your
homework, take a look.
I actually recommend doing
this homework a couple
of different times and seeing
if you can explore different sort
of brands or effects that you can get,
maybe play around with those
cartoony shadows that we saw
on Duolingo or some of the
more skeuomorphic shadows
and lighting effects that we
saw in harvest, et cetera.
If you have any questions,
post them in the student community
and we'll see you in the next lesson.